▍2026 美网 男单半决赛
兹维列夫 6-3 7-6⁷ 7-6⁶ 哈恰诺夫 · 赛后新闻发布会
Hello.
你好
Sasha, a highly contested three-set win.
萨沙，苦战三盘取胜
We advance and move on.
我们晋级了，继续前进
Your thoughts?
你的想法呢
Straight-set win, but anything
直落三盘获胜，但
but straightforward in a way.
过程一点也不轻松
He played incredibly well,
他打得非常好
fought incredibly well.
拼得也非常凶
Second and third set,
第二盘和第三盘
I think it's more than obvious
我觉得再明显不过了
that they could have gone both ways.
胜负可能就在毫厘之间
And I just played a few points better here
我只是在这儿那儿
and there.
多赢了几分
And I'm happy with the win.
我对这场胜利感到高兴
Well, congratulations once again.
再次恭喜你
Questions?
有问题吗
You referenced not playing well
你提到过自己打得不好
at the start of the tournament
在赛事刚开始的时候
when you were in your on-court interview.
当时在场上采访里说的
Have you ever had a tournament
你有没有经历过一届赛事
where you've started at a lower level
从较低的水平起步
and made so much improvement across
却取得了这么大的进步
the duration of it?
在整届赛事的过程里？
Because you've gone from, if it was low
因为你从很低的状态
for you, at an extreme height.
一路走到了极高处
It's a great question.
问得好
I feel like when I made the final here
我觉得我打进那次决赛时
in 2020, I didn't play well,
2020年，我打得不好
but I didn't play well the entire tournament.
但那整个赛事我都打得不好
That never changed, funny enough.
说来好笑，状态一直没变
And I made it to the final,
我还是打进了决赛
and I was two points away from winning.
而且离夺冠只差两分
But I think the improvement
但我觉得进步
has been quite dramatic for me.
对我来说相当显著
And it's a great thing
这是件好事
because I really started off the tournament,
因为赛事开局的时候
and I was like, well, this is pointless
我心想，这有什么意义
because I'm not going to do anything here.
因为我在这儿不会有作为
And here I am sitting and preparing
而现在我坐在这里备战
for a Sunday final.
周日的决赛
So things like that can happen in sports
体育里就是会有这种事
and tennis in general.
网球也一样
Things can change very quickly
情况可以变得很快
for the positive or negative.
可能变好也可能变坏
And for me, luckily, it was for the positive.
对我来说幸运的是变好了
And now I'm going
现在我会
to do everything I can to prepare
尽我所能去准备
for Sunday.
周日的比赛
Well done, Sasha.
干得好，萨沙
Can I ask you about the ball bouncing?
我能问一下关于拍球的事吗
It seems to be like I've really increased.
感觉次数真的多了很多
Yeah, I have no idea why.
是啊，我完全不知道为什么。
I'm not doing it on purpose.
我不是故意的。
I just saw the stat.
我就是看到了那个数字
I bounced it 12,000 times or something like
我颠了大概一万两千次
that.
还是多少
That's quite funny.
那挺有意思
I mean, are you trying to get it like a seven?
我是说，你想拍到七下？
No, I'm not.
不，我没有。
I'm not counting in my head.
我没在心里数
I'm not getting a certain number
我也没有一个特定的目标数字
or anything like that.
或者类似的东西
I don't know why it increased so much.
我不知道为什么它涨了这么多
I think today it decreased again
我觉得今天它又降了
because I saw it before the semifinal.
因为我半决赛前看到了
So I was like, OK, it's got to go less.
我就想，好吧，得少点
But then I forget about it every once
但过一阵我又忘了
in a while, and it goes up
然后它又涨上去
to, I don't know what number it is.
涨到我不知道是多少了
What happens that makes you stop
发生什么会让你停下来
and makes you be like, OK, now I got it out,
让你觉得，好，颠够了
and now I can start?
现在我可以开始了？
No clue.
不知道
Honestly, like really honestly, no idea.
说真的，完全没头绪
Just talk a little bit about these last six years
再谈谈过去这六年吧
because obviously the 2020 final
因为显然2020年的决赛
is a very strange atmosphere.
氛围非常奇怪
Nothing going to be similar
周日那场不会有任何
to that on Sunday.
和那时候相似的地方
And just your own sort
那么你自己
of journey in these last six years
在这六年里
between US Open Finals.
两次美网决赛之间的历程
Yeah, I think a lot has happened.
是的，我觉得发生了很多事
I've played in a lot of other finals.
我打了很多其他决赛
I played a lot of big matches since then.
从那时起我打了很多重要比赛
Back then, of course,
那时候，当然
it was my first Grand Slam final.
那是我第一次打进大满贯决赛
I was inexperienced.
我那时经验不足
I was still a young guy, I would say.
我还是个年轻人，可以说
Yeah, just different.
对，就是不一样
Everything is different.
一切都不一样了
And I am pretty sure that the atmosphere
而且我很确定现场氛围
is going to be very, very different on Sunday
周日会非常非常不一样
as well, no matter who I play.
而且，不管我的对手是谁
So what I'm looking forward
所以我很期待
to that, I think it's going
这一点，我觉得会
to be a fantastic feeling playing a final
打这场决赛会很美妙
in a sold out Arthur Ashe
在座无虚席的阿瑟·阿什
and not in an empty one.
而不是一个空球场
Did 2020 leave any particular scar tissue
2020年留下什么心结吗
for you?
对你来说？
It did, until I won in Paris.
有过，直到我在巴黎赢了
I think there was question marks,
我觉得当时确实有问号，
there was doubts whether I was ever going
也有人怀疑我到底
to win one for sure.
能不能赢下一个。
I talked about it quite openly
我之前很坦诚地聊过这件事，
before, but now that I've won one, it's OK.
但现在赢了一个，就没事了
There.
好的。
Hi, Alexander.
嗨，亚历山大。
At the end of last year,
去年年底，
you talked about the importance
你谈到打得更具攻击性的网球
of playing more aggressive tennis,
有多重要，
and that's shown itself,
这一点已经展现出来
particularly in the Wimbledon final
尤其是在温网决赛
and many other matches this year.
以及今年其他许多比赛中
When you're in the moment,
当你在场上时
is that a conscious decision
这是你刻意做出的决定
or a conscious effort you have to make
还是你必须刻意努力
to make yourself do that, like, say,
让自己做到那样，比如
you did at the end of the match today?
就像你今天最后那样？
I would say no.
我会说不
I would say it's a conscious decision
我会说，这是一个刻意的决定
that you're doing it
你要做的是
in practice every single day
每天在训练里做这件事
so that it becomes automatic in a match.
到比赛里它就成了本能
In a match, you shouldn't think.
在比赛中，你不应该思考
You shouldn't think
你不应该思考
of whether I should make this decision now
是现在该做这个决定
or this decision now.
还是现在做那个决定
I think everything should just be a flow.
我认为一切都应该是一种心流
And the flow starts with how you practice
而心流始于你如何训练
and what you do in practice.
以及你在训练中做什么
It's as simple as that, because in tennis,
就这么简单，因为网球里
you've got a maximum amount
你最多只有
of one second between every shot.
每一拍之间的一秒钟
You don't have time to think.
你没有时间去思考
You shouldn't be thinking.
你不应该思考
And I think it's about the practice sessions
我觉得关键在赛前训练
that you do beforehand.
就是你事先做的那些练习
As you mentioned,
正如你所说
sold out at Ashe Stadium for Sunday.
阿瑟·阿什球场周日售罄
You'll be facing an American.
你将迎战一位美国选手
We don't know which one yet,
我们还不知道是哪一位
but you have a very strong record
但你对这两位选手
against both those players.
都有非常出色的交手记录。
What are your thoughts
你怎么看
about them individually,
他们各自的特点，
starting with Frances, please?
先从蒂亚福说起吧？
Frances is somebody that can do anything
蒂亚福是那种球员
with a tennis ball.
拿球能做出任何事
He can be aggressive.
他可以打得很凶
He can also mess around with it a little bit.
他也会偶尔玩点花样
He can be tricky to play, for sure.
和他交手确实很难缠
I have massive respect for him.
我非常尊重他
Also, I've known him
而且我认识他
for almost 20 years now, similar to Karen,
快20年了，跟哈恰诺夫一样
actually.
其实
And Ben is just a big, powerful guy.
谢尔顿是个高大强壮的人
Massive serve, massive ground strokes.
发球和底线都极具威力
Everything he does is just big.
他做什么都很大力
They're a bit of a different style
他们的风格有点不同
of tennis player,
类型的网球选手
but they're both very exciting, I think.
但我觉得他们俩都很精彩
Is the crowd a challenge
观众是种挑战
or something different for you?
还是对你来说有所不同
No, I enjoy these kind of atmospheres.
不 我很享受这种氛围
I've said it before.
我以前也说过
I mean, I played a lot of French guys
我跟很多法国球员交过手
in France.
在法国。
I think the most hostile crowd, if you call it
我觉得最敌对的观众
that, is when you're playing French
就是当年对阵法国球员
in Paris-Bercy back in the day.
在巴黎贝尔西的时候
That was quite intense,
那场面相当激烈
and I always enjoyed those.
我一直很享受那些比赛
I always enjoyed those kind
我一直很享受那种
of atmospheres.
氛围。
Of course, I played Australian guys
当然，我也跟澳大利亚球员
in Australia.
在澳大利亚打过
I played Arthur Fery now in Wimbledon.
我刚在温网跟费里交手
The Wimbledon crowd is a bit different,
不过温网的观众不一样
though.
就是了。
There's no question about that.
这一点毫无疑问
But for me, a loud and energetic crowd
但对我来说，热闹的观众
is always great, as long as they're fair,
总是好事，只要他们公正
as long as they don't interrupt in the middle
只要他们不在比赛进行中打断
of points.
在回合中间
I always enjoy these kind of atmospheres.
我总是很享受这种氛围
Last two in English, and then Matt.
最后两位用英语，然后是马特
Ciao. Congratulations.
你好，祝贺你
You played also Italians in Italy.
你在意大利也跟意大利人打过
But the general impression
但总的印象
is that you changed after you won the Paris.
是你赢下巴黎之后变了
Now you're more relaxed.
现在你更放松了
You smile much more, and so on.
你笑得更多了，诸如此类
And I saw smiling also your father
我还看到你父亲在笑
in these days.
就这几天。
Really, I didn't.
真的？我没看到。
It's very rare.
这非常罕见。
非常罕见。
I didn't see that.
我没看到那个。
Yeah, so is also the team more confident,
那团队是不是也更有信心
I mean, more relaxed
我的意思是，更放松
when you are with your brother, father?
和你哥哥、父亲在一起时？
The old spirit have changed or not?
原来那种劲头变了没有？
No, I think not much has changed,
不，我觉得没有太大改变
to be honest.
说实话。
I think, yeah, of course,
我觉得，是的，当然
winning one was the ultimate goal.
赢下一个本来是终极目标
But now we want more.
但现在我们想要更多。
We want to achieve bigger things.
我们想要实现更大的事情。
And we're still working very hard towards
而且我们仍然非常努力地朝着
that.
那个目标努力。
We're still very focused towards that.
我们仍然非常专注于那一点
And I think everybody has still a goal
我觉得每个人心里都有目标
in their vision.
在他们的视野中
Last question in English, Matt.
最后一个问题用英语，马特
So you have more grand slam finals
所以你今年打进的大满贯决赛
than both Carlos and Jannik this year.
比阿尔卡拉斯和辛纳都多
And you may actually end up
而你实际上可能最终会
with more titles.
拿到更多冠军。
And then is that something you
这是不是你当时
would have thought might be possible back
就觉得有可能做到的事
in December?
在去年十二月？
I believed in it.
我一直相信。
I believe that is possible.
我相信这是有可能的。
I think not many of you guys did.
我觉得你们没多少人信
I think the question was always,
我觉得问题一直是
is Carlos and Jannik going
阿尔卡拉斯和辛纳会不会
to play all four grand slam finals
再次在四大满贯决赛中
between each other again?
彼此交手
Yeah, of course, a very legit question
是的 当然 这个问题很合理
with how the last two years went.
考虑到过去两年的走势
I mean, I'm happy with how this year went
我是说，今年的走势
so far.
到现在我挺满意
But I got another big match on Sunday
但周日我还有一场重要比赛
and that's my focus.
那才是我的重心
Okay, let's switch to German.
好的 我们切换德语
Thank you. Thank you.
谢谢 谢谢